Jagannāth is Kṛṣṇa in Dvārakā
Jagannath es Krsna en Dwaraka
feeling incomparable separation from Vṛndāvan,
sintiendo una separación incomparable por Vrindavan
from Rādhārāṇī and the Vraja-gopīs in Vṛndāvan.
por Radharani y las Braja gopis que están en Vrindavan
That’s who Jagannāth is. That’s why He looks like that.
ese es Jagannath.
[The Gift of Appreciation]
El Obsequio del Aprecio
This is an ecstatic transformation of feeling separation
Es una transformación debida al éxtasis
So, if in that position, you can take, begin
Así es que si en esa posición , puedes empezar
—talking about beginnings— if you can begin to take Him to Vṛndāvan,
hablando acerca de inicios- si puedes llevar a Krsna hacia Vrindavan
what better beginning could you ever conceive of beginnings?
¿Que mejor inicio de entre todos los inicios podrás concebir?
What beginning would be superior to this one?
¿Qué inicio podrá ser superior a éste?
It’s the ultimate beginning. The best, ever.
Es el inicio final. El mejor, por siempre.
I remember hearing Prabhupād say,
Recuerdo a Prabhupada decir,
“It’s the emotional ecstasy of taking Kṛṣṇa to Vṛndāvan.”
él decía "Es el éxtasis emocional
Because when I joined, ’71,
Puesto que cuando me uní en el 71
around the—by Gurudev’s grace— Nṛsiṁha Chaturdaśī, a few days before,
aproximandamente- por la gracia de Gurudev- el Nrisimha Chaturdasi, unos días antes,
the Daśamī, which was the day after my birthday,
el Dashami, el cual fue el día antes de mi cumpleaños,
so it all worked out …
y todo era como una preparación
So within two months, Prabhupād showed up
y en los siguientes dos meses, Prabhupada apareció
in San Francisco for the Ratha Yātrā.
en San Francisco, para el Rathayatra.
And I once said to Guru Mahārāj about it,
Y una vez le comenté esto a Guru Maharaj
and so many others were very young,
y otros eran muy jóvenes también
and suddenly we were like, immersed,
y de pronto estábamos como sumergidos
—you talk about immersion, total immersion—
si hablas de sumergir, sumergidos totalmente-
we were totally immersed in all of these things
de forma total en todas éstas cosas
and on some level, I was saying, on some level appreciating it.
y a cierto nivel, yo diría, lo estábamos apreciando
And Guru Mahārāj said, “Yes, He extended you
Y Guru Maharaj me dijo "Sí. El te extendía
the capacity to appreciate it.”
la capacidad para apreciarlo."
That’s what it is.
Eso es lo que es.
That’s what the whole of Kṛṣṇa consciousness is,
De eso se trata la totalidad de la conciencia de Krsna
the extended appreciation, capacity, to appreciate it;
El aprecio extendido, la capacidad para apreciarlo.
what Mahāprabhu did to Sārvabhauma;
Lo que Mahaprabhu le hizo a Serabhauma,
what everyone, every extension, of Kṛṣṇa consciousness
lo que todos, cada extensión de la conciencia de Krsna
has ever been; a gracious merciful extension,
ha sido siempre, una llena de gracia y misericordiosa extensión
extended capacity, to appreciate that.
la extensión de la capacidad para poder apreciarla.
Reality for Itself, by Itself.
La realidad es por sí misma y para sí misma.
Guru-rūpa-harim gauram:
guru-rupa harim gauram
Mahāprabhu comes in Rādhārāṇī’s [mood]
Mahaprabhu ha venido en el humor de Radharani
to preach Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
a predicar la conciencia de Krsna
Why didn’t he preach some other way?
¿Por qué no predicó de algún otro modo?
Because there’s nothing superior to that, He couldn’t th[ink] …
Porque no hay nada superior a eso que se pueda pensar
When He saw what She has, that awakened in Him
Cuando vemos lo que Ella tiene, eso despierta en Él
the tendency to distribute this also.
la tendencia a distribuirlo también.
The highest thing. The best.
Lo más elevado. Lo mejor.
And it reaches its zenith at this pastime.
Y alcanza su cenit en éste pasatiempo.
And that’s why Guru Mahārāj says,
Y por ello Guru Maharaj decía.
Saraswatī Ṭhākur: “Vṛndāvan’s for the shallow thinkers.”
Saraswati Thakur: "Vrindavan es para los pensadores superficiales"
He got that from Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur,
Él obtuvo eso de Bhaktivinod Thakur.
“Kurukṣetra’s for the man of real bhajan.”
"Kurukshetra para el hombre de bhajan verdadero."
Now we’re back to this, saying,
Ahora regresando a lo anterior, decía
because separation has reached it’s zenith,
porque la separación alcanza su cenit,
whoever will render service at that time
quienquiera que rinda servicio en ese momento
will draw the maximum remuneration.
obtendrá la máxima remuneración.
That’s why it’s the best time,
Por ello es el mejor momento
and that’s why on this day, at this time,
y es por ello que éste día, éste momento,
with this concept and this understanding,
con éste concepto y entendimiento
Guru Mahārāj began Śrī Chaitanya Sāraswat Maṭh.
Guru Mahraj dio inicio al Sri Chaitanya Swaraswat Math
It’s the beginning of the Śrī Chaitanya Sāraswat Maṭh.
Es el comienzo del Sri Chaitanya Saraswat Math.
This moment, this point.
Este momento, este punto.
Nothing Guru Mahārāj does is by accident,
Nada de lo que Guru Maharaj hace es accidental,
and everything is multi-layered, multi-dimensional,
y todo tiene diversas cubiertas, muchas dimensiones
and profound to the infinite degree.
y profundiza hasta el grado infinito
He’s bringing you in connection with the pinnacle
El te lleva hacia la conexión con el pináculo
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
de la conciencia de Krsna
that’s when he starts; his Maṭh springs out of that plane,
ahí es donde él empezó, su Math surge desde ese plano
and his Maṭh proper takes people into that plane.
Y el Math apropiadamente lleva a la gente hacia ese plano.
That’s what he’s doing,
Eso es lo que esta haciendo.
and that’s why nothing compares to it.
y por ello nada se le compara.